After the disappearance of Srila Saraswati Thakur
Śrīla Sarasvatī Ṭhākura eltávozása után
the devotees all ... They were looking for guidance and direction.
minden bhakta tanácsot és iránymutatást várt.
[Book Bhagavatam | Person Bhagavatam]
[Bhāgavatam könyv | Bhāgavatam személy]
“What do we do now?
"Mit tegyünk most?
Prabhupad Saraswati Thakur has left the world,
Prabhupāda Sarasvatī Ṭhākura elhagyta ezt a világot,
how will we get guidance?
ki fog minket vezetni?
The darkness of the kali-yuga is setting in,
A Kali-yuga sötétsége elkezdődött,
we will lose our ways certainly,
biztos el fogunk tévedni,
how will we go on?”
hogyan haladjunk tovább?"
And they turned to one Maharaj
És akkor egy Mahārājához fordultak,
known as Nemi Maharaj, Gabhastinemi Maharaj,
akit Nemi Mahārājának hívtak, Gabhastinemi Mahārājának:
“Please help us, advise us, guide us.”
"Kérlek segíts nekünk, adj tanácsot, vezess minket."
And he quoted the Bhagavatam sloka,
Erre ő a Bhāgavatamból idézett egy ślokát:
kṛṣṇe sva-dhāmopagate dharma-jñānādibhiḥ saha
kṛṣṇe sva-dhāmopagate dharma-jñānādibhiḥ saha
kalau naṣṭa-dṛśām eṣa purāṇārko 'dhunoditaḥ [SB: 1.3.43]
kalau naṣṭa-dṛśām eṣa purāṇārko 'dhunoditaḥ [SB: 1.3.43]
When Krishna left the world, it was plunged into the darkness of the kali-yuga,
Mikor Kṛṣṇa elhagyta a világot, az alámerült a Kali-yuga sötétségében,
but the Bhagavat Purana has risen like the sun,
azonban a Bhāgavata Purāṇa felemelkedett, mint a kelő nap,
like sometimes we take it an eighteen thousand rayed sun,
tizennyolcezer napsugárral
each sloka like a ray,
ahol minden śloka egy-egy napsugár,
this sun has risen to illuminate Krishna-conception
és ez a nap felemelkedett, hogy megvilágítsa a Kṛṣṇa tudatot,
and give guidance to everyone.
és irányt mutasson.
So he is saying, “Now we will take our direction from the Bhagavatam”.
Szóval azt mondta: "Mostantól a Bhāgavatam fog minket vezérelni."
This was his response.
Ez volt az ő válasza.
And it’s told that
És azt mondják, hogy
the senior disciples of Srila Saraswati Thakur,
Śrīla Sarasvatī Ṭhākura régi tanítványai
they turned to Srila Guru Maharaj and said,
Śrīla Guru Mahārājához fordultak:
“What do you say to that?
"Mit gondolsz te erről?
He’s saying,
Szerinte,
“Now, that Prabhupad, our guru, [is gone] we’ll take guidance from the book Bhagavatam.
"Most, hogy Prabhupāda, a tanítónk [eltávozott], a Bhāgavatam könyv fog minket irányítani.
The person Bhagavata [is gone], now we go to the book Bhagavat.
A személy Bhāgavatam [eltávozott], így a könyv Bhāgavatamot követjük.
What do you say?”
Mit mondasz te erre?"
And Guru Maharaj responded by saying,
És Guru Mahārāja azt válaszolta:
“We are not sikhs.”
"Mi nem vagyunk szikhek."
[In] the sikh religion they worship the book called the Granth Sahib,
A szikh vallásban egy nagy könyvet imádnak, a Granth Száhibot,
they bring out this ... If you ever been to, you’ve seen ...
előhozzák azt... ha valaha jártál arra, akkor láthattad...
they bring out a giant book and they do a puj ... They worship this book.
előhozzák azt a hatalmas könyvet és imádják ezt a könyvet.
So Guru Maharaj said, “We are not sikhs”,
Szóval ezért mondta Guru Mahārāja, hogy 'Mi nem vagyunk szikhek',
he said, “We worship the Vaishnava.
és úgy folytatta: "Mi a vaiṣṇavákat imádjuk.
And amongst us who is perceived
És aki közülünk láthatóan
as the highest Vaishnava or the best Vaishnava,
a legmagasabb vaiṣṇavának vagy legjobb vaiṣṇavának tekinthető,
we will take direction from him.”
mi tőle fogunk iránymutatást kapni."
So we always say, “Sādhu, Śāstra, Guru, Vaiṣṇava”—
Ahogy mindig ismételjük: "Sādhu, Śāstra, Guru, Vaiṣṇava" —
these things are running in parallel,
ezek mind párhuzamosan működnek,
should be running in parallel to one another.
együtt kell, hogy működjenek egymással.
It’s a system, in a sense, of checks and balances.
Egyfajta rendszere a visszajelzésnek és egyensúlynak.